So this course is totally based on hands on training of programming and practical demonstration of RFID
tags.
But this section is specifically based on RFID theory.
And trust me, this theory is really important and it will create the base for our coming lectures.
So we will start with the basics and see what RFID is.
So RFID works on radio frequency principle, and it consists of two main components the RFID tag and
the RFID reader.
RFID reader continuously sends radio frequency waves.
And whenever the tag is in the range of this RFID reader it sends.
Whenever the tag hits the frequency signals so the reader gets its feedback and then the communication
starts and we will see all those things in really detail.
It's just a high level overview of what RFID system is, right?
You don't have to worry about if you don't understand anything in this lecture.
It's just a high level overview of RFID system and what are the components in RFID system.
We will get into complete detail of how RFID tags work and how the reader works and what type of reader
we are going to use.
We are going to cover each and everything in the coming lectures and types of RFID frequencies.
There are three basic types of RFID frequency the low frequency Lf, which operates in one 25kHz and
one 34kHz.
And then there is high frequency which operates in 13.56MHz.
And then there is ultra high frequency UHF, which operates on 860 and nine 60MHz.
And it depends on the country you are surrounded and the laws of that country.
Right?
So the range of Lf is in between 10 to 8 to ten centimeters.
And you you have to touch the reader with the tag to read low frequency.
And then there is high frequency and its range is around one meter and then there is ultra high frequency.
It range around 10m to 15m.
So in this course our main focus will be high frequency tags and we will see how high frequency tags
work and what type of high frequency readers are available in the market.
We are not starting with low frequency because low frequency consists of very less security or there
is no security.
So we will start with high frequency and once you will understand how high frequency works, it will
be very easy for you to program low frequency tags as well.
And we will not cover ultra high frequency as well because ultra high frequency tags are similar based
on high frequency, but ultra high frequency tags are expensive and their readers are also very expensive.
So our main focus will be high frequency tags.
And trust me, if you understand how high frequency tags work, it will be very easy for you to program
low frequency tags as well as ultra high frequency tags.
So we will see how high frequency tags work and what are the standards of high frequency and what are
the what what is the structure of high frequency tags?
We will see all those things in very detail.
And then there is applications of RFID.
There are whole lot of applications of RFID, starting with access control.
That is the basic of RFID.
And and we will create one practical tool of access control as well using RFID.
And we are going to see both the the standard way of creating the access control tool and what are the
bad standards in the market.
We are going to see both the things in our coming lectures.
And once you understand how access control work on RFID, tracking, library books, grocery store items
and tracking animal is a piece of cake.
We are also going to see transportation and logistics use of RFID tags.
So our main focus will be on access control and how a access control works in RFID.
We are going to program and see the tools which we are going to use this.
This will be our main focus, right?
Because in access control you see a actual potential of RFID.
So this is what RFID is.
RFID is based on radio frequency, as I told you.
And there are two main components of RFID, the RFID reader and the RFID tag.
We are going to see what tags we are going to use and what are the types of RFID reader that's coming
in in the coming lectures.
So and we have also seen what type of frequencies are available in the market for RFID.
And our main focus will be frequency, as I told you.
And the applications of RFID.
So this is coming in our coming lectures.
So stay tuned.